Directions. In this section, you will hear two long conversations.
At the end of each conversation, you will hear four questions.
Both the conversation and the questions will be spoken only once.
After you hear a question, you must choose the best answer from the four choices
marked A, B, C, and D.
Then mark the corresponding letter on answer sheet 1 with the single line through
the center. Conversation 1 Welcome to Money Matters, a weekly program that helps you
manage your money.
Tonight, I'll be talking to Mary Johnson about budgeting.
Hello, everyone. There's a magic about money.
When it's not planned for, tracked, and kept a record of, it literally disappears.
What are some of the steps we can take to prevent this from happening?
Well, it's all about keeping track of your money.
If you don't do that, you'll never be able to set any goals for your budget or have
the discipline to stick to them.
That's easier said than done.
I read recently that only 41 of Americans adhere to a budget.
Yes, but knowing what you earn and what you spend can give you reassurance that you
won't get into debt in the first place.
You can do this by adding up all of your sources of income you have and writing them
all down on a piece of paper.
On the same page, write down all of your monthly expenses.
I'm always amazed at how much my expenses add up.
But designating each item as an income or an expense really helps me have a much
better sense of all my spending.
Right. Most people have no idea how much they spend each day, let alone each week or
month, no matter how careful they are.
Next, subtract your monthly expenses from income.
If the result is positive, you are living within your means.
If the result is a negative number, you're going to have to cut back on your
spending. I'm usually a negative number.
I just can't resist the allure of all those prestigious goods.
Well, it's not a catastrophe, but you do have to make some changes.
Try cutting back on those non -essential items.
Sell some stuff in your attic or shop online to avoid unnecessary temptations like
chocolate. Failing that, you can always find yourself a part -time job.
Questions 1 to 4 are based on the conversation you have just heard.
Question 1. What does the man say about the weekly program?
Question 2. What did the man read recently?
Question 3. What does the woman suggest the man do first to avoid getting into debt?
Question 4. What does the woman say about online shopping?
Question 5. does man first
Question What the woman suggest man do first to avoid debt?
Question What woman man do getting into Question 10.
Nice to meet you.
I spoke to all your references, and they all checked out okay.
So let me show you around.
The place actually belongs to my mother, but her health isn't great, so we finally
managed to persuade her to move in with us and rent this old place out.
It's a great size, plenty of space, very versatile.
I think it's a winner for us.
Yes, all the appliances are brand new.
There's a washing machine and a tumble dryer in the utility room next to the
kitchen. Lots of closet space too, which is fabulous.
My wife has a ridiculous number of shoes.
Now, the big question.
What about noise and the neighbors?
Well, all the neighbors are elderly, so no noisy kids and the back of the house
overlooks a clear and peaceful pond.
So it's perfect if tranquility is what you are looking for.
That's good news.
We've been living in a less than glamorous part of Aberdeen, constantly harassed day
and night by noisy neighbors.
Getting to work was a nightmare too, as we only have one car and my wife has to use
it as she works nights at the hospital.
Well, if you like the place, it's yours as soon as I get a contract drawn up with
the solicitor. The first month's rent and a deposit are mandatory on signing the
contract. Then we can work out when is the best day for you to pay rent each month.
We'll be incredibly happy to be your new tenants.
Thank you so much.
My wife will be thrilled to get out of the shabby place we are now in and start
filling those wardrobes with all those shoes.
Questions five to eight are based on the conversation you have just heard.
Question five. What does the woman say about the
Question six. What is the man's chief consideration in looking for a flat?
Question seven. What does the man have to do on signing the contract?
Question eight. Why does the man say his wife will feel very excited if they move
into the Section B.
Directions. In this section, you will hear two passages.
At the end of each passage, you will hear three or four questions.
Both the passage and the questions will be spoken only once.
After you hear a question, you must choose the best answer from the four choices
marked A, B, C, and D.
Then, mark the corresponding letter on answer sheet one with a single line through
the center. Passage one.
A new study has found a positive correlation between how much television children
watch and their parents' stress levels.
Why? Because the more television kids watch, the more they're exposed to
advertising. The more advertising they see, the more likely they are to insist on
purchasing items when they go with their parents to the store.
This could generate conflict if the parents refuse.
All that, researchers say, can contribute to parents'
stress levels. What's the solution?
Perhaps the most obvious is curtailing screen time.
Commercial content is there for a reason, to elicit purchasing behavior.
So, parents might want to shut off the TV.
Researchers concede that this is easier said than done, so they suggest another
option. Parents can change how they talk to their kids about purchases.
The researchers suggest that parents seek input from their children on family
purchasing decisions.
They shouldn't try to control all purchases.
Instead, parents might tell their children things like, I will listen to your advice
on certain products or brands.
This type of communication, the researchers assert, can lead to children making
fewer purchasing demands.
That means less parents' stress.
However, the protective effect of this kind of diminishes with greater exposure to
television. This is because advertising aimed at children is especially persuasive.
Advertisers use an assortment of tactics, such as bright colors, happy music, and
celebrity endorsements, to appeal to children.
Plus, children don't have the cognitive ability to fully understand advertising's
intent. That makes them particularly vulnerable to advertisements.
Questions 9 to 11 are based on the passage you have just heard.
Question 9. What has the new study found about children watching television?
Question 10. What are parents advised to do to reduce the impact of TV commercials?
Question 11. What makes children particularly vulnerable to TV commercials?
What TV Everyone is supposed to for good guys, and we should only punish the bad
guys. But that's not what we always do.
Most of the time, we do indeed reward good people.
We also often punish people who harm others or who aren't good team players.
But sometimes, the good guys also get punished or criticized.
Specifically, because they are so good.
This seems baffling, because it's detrimental to group cooperation.
However, the phenomenon has been discovered in multiple fields, and it has been
found in every society.
Why does this happen?
Research suggests a simple reason.
When one person looks really good, others look bad by comparison.
Those others then have an incentive in stopping that person from looking good.
Especially if they can't or won't compete.
After all, we're all judged in comparison with others.
When faced with someone better, what can a normal person do?
One option is to actively compete.
A second option is to bring that person down.
That is, to suppress their cooperation or work ethic, infer selfish motives for
their actions, or imply real or imagined hypocrisy.
Other tactics include attacking them on unrelated dimensions or punishing them
outright. Why does this matter?
often attack the motives of people who protect the environment,
donate money, or work too hard.
Such good deeds are dismissed as naive or hypocritical by those who do not perform
those deeds. This criticism may ultimately discourage people from doing good deeds.
So it's important to recognize these attacks for what they are.
Question 13. How are we all judged, according to the passage?
Question 14. What can a normal person do when faced with people who perform better?
Question 15. What may discourage people from performing good deeds?
Section C. Directions.
In this section, will hear three recordings of lectures or talks, followed by three
or four questions.
The recordings will be played only once.
After you hear a question, you must choose the best answer from the four choices
marked A, B, C, and D.
Then mark the corresponding letter On answer sheet 1, with the single line through
the center. Recording 1.
In America, most researchers concede that boys and girls are brought up in different
ways, taught different skills, and rewarded for different acts.
Women, it is agreed, excel at certain tasks, men at others.
There is little argument that some personality traits appear more dominant in one
sex than in the other.
All of this notwithstanding, gender differences are very much in the media these
days. Since the rise of the women's movement, gender role behavior has come under
closer scrutiny. How has this affected friendship?
How do the sexes differ in their friendship relations?
Most pre -teen children have a best friend who is usually someone of the same sex
and similar age.
Both sexes share an essentially positive recollection of these childhood
friendships. They do not differ in this respect.
However, the type of engaged in during these early friendships is telling of the
difference to come.
Boys tend to form play groups that are competitive in nature.
Girls groups more frequently revolve around cooperative enterprises.
Thus, at an early age, boys become concerned with trying hard and winning, while
girls, by contrast, play house and school, engaging in roles that require
complementary support.
Speaking of their childhood, men recall being highly responsive to and aware of the
gender role opinions of other boys.
Girls in pre -teen years appear to be less susceptible to gender role pressure.
It is not until the dating years that women report being concerned with feminine
behavior. Males, for the most part, are responsive to the suggestion that their
behavior is unmanly at almost any age.
These early attitudes, reinforced by social conditioning, continue to play an active
part in the friendships of both sexes during adolescence.
This is a period when the majority of once again report a close alliance with same
-sex friends. Now, however, with heightened intensity, considerable energy is
devoted to competing for position, and a definite undercurrent of competition
permeates the relationship.
Although in dissimilar fashion, females share equally fragile relationships at this
age. For them, the bond of loyalty extends only to the line of romantic involvement.
This is most apt to be the case in late adolescence, when dating and relationships
with boys take sharp precedence over sisterhood.
Actually, dating dilutes the intensity of same -sex friendships for men also.
For the majority of us, the moment we begin to date seriously, there's a competition
between romance and friendship.
Questions 16 to 18 are based on the recording you have just heard.
Question 16. What does the speaker say about most preteen children?
Question 17. What do most males devote much of their energy to during adolescence?
Question 18. What do children do when they reach late adolescence?
Good afternoon. In today's lecture, we'll be talking about how and when to disclose
a disability when applying for a job.
On average, about 20 of the population has some form of disability.
Most countries these days have equal opportunity and non -discrimination laws.
Yet, disabled people often find it hard to decide when, how, and, if at all, to
raise their disability problem with a potential employer.
There is uncertainty about how a recruiter will perceive their disability.
As such, many candidates fear they wouldn't be considered for a position as a of
disclosing this personal information.
And research has validated this as a genuine concern for many job applicants.
It's a natural reaction, but it shouldn't be a reason to stay quiet.
People need to remember that they are applying for a position they have the skills
and experience to excel in.
Discussing a disability with a potential employer may help them make reasonable
workplace adjustments in their favor.
It's most appropriate to discuss a disability when they reply to confirm an
interview. This information needn't be put up front in their cover letter or resume
because it's probably not relevant to the position itself.
Candidates with disabilities should feel they have the power to make their own
decisions around sharing this information free from prejudice.
If they find an organization that doesn't celebrate diversity and inclusion, it
could say a lot about the company's culture.
Perhaps the organization isn't the right fit.
It's important for them to remember that they are seeking a manager and employer
that's going to be supportive and continue to give them a great employment
experience. Companies sometimes offer candidates the chance to disclose disabilities
on their application form.
But people shouldn't feel restricted by this method or timing.
People should avoid sharing the name of their disability or condition.
There is always the risk that the recruiter will research information that is
inaccurate or irrelevant.
If people don't think their disability will impact their ability to perform in the
advertised position,
then it's entirely their entitlement to choose when and whether to share this
information. Questions 19 to 21 are based on the recording you have just heard.
Question 19. Why do disabled job applicants feel reluctant to disclose their
disability information?
Question 20. When does the speaker suggest applicants reveal their disability
information? Question 21.
What are people advised to do when filling out their job application form?
Recording 3. Smartphones distract attention and reduce learning because of their
potential to offer activities more inviting than study.
But what about background sound alone?
A group of American researchers compared students' comprehension of verbal material
when reading in the presence of background speech, instrumental music, or general
noise. General noise is neutral, such as that from the sound of an air conditioner
or fan. Students' scores were most depressed in the presence of background speech.
Comprehension was slightly better with the presence of music than with speech.
However, when they were asked to identify melodies rather than understand text,
background music interfered more.
When the background speech was in a language unfamiliar to participants, there was
little, if any, hindrance of reading comprehension.
British researchers compared the effects of background speech, vocal music,
instrumental music, general background noise, and silence on short -term memory.
Background speech had the biggest negative effect.
Vocal music was slightly more disruptive than instrumental.
In general, background noise and silence were least disruptive.
It seems the degree of interference from background noise depends on the overlap
between the processing required on the task and the processing required to screen
out the background noise.
The studies suggest that when people read and when they try to remember any verbal
material, background speech will inhibit their ability.
Instrumental music will have, at worst, a slight effect.
When students write essays, however, other research has found it is best to reduce
all background noise as much as possible.
Not everyone reacts in the same way to distractions.
Other studies suggest some aspects of personality may make a difference.
The researchers subjected shy, quiet people and confident, outgoing ones to high
-arousal or low -arousal background music, general noise, or silence while asking
them to remember words.
Everyone performed best in the silent condition, but less sociable people were more
negatively affected by each of distractions.
So, when children are reading and trying to incorporate new material, parents could
consider allowing some background music, particularly if it is instrumental, and
their child is the outgoing type.
Questions 22 to 25 are based on the recording you have just heard.
Question 22. What did some American researchers find about students' reading
comprehension in the presence of background noise?
Question 23. What do we learn from the British researchers about the degree of
interference from background noise?
Question 24. What is best for students to do when writing essays according to some
research? Question 25.
How do people of different personalities react to distractions according